Guide to the Coleman Brothers Collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Coleman Brothers Collection
1721-1910
1821-1868
Ms Coll 36
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1
(2 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence between Isaac Pearson Coleman and James Beakes Coleman, brothers who received medical degrees at the Medical Institution of Yale College (Yale School of Medicine) and who practiced medicine in and near Trenton, New Jersey; correspondence of the Coleman brothers with medical colleagues and with members of their families; letters, manuscripts, and legal documents pertaining to the extended Coleman family of New Jersey as well as the Saltar family; and portrait photographs of the extended Coleman family.
Coleman, Isaac Pearson, 1804-1869
Coleman, James Beakes, 1805-1877
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased 2012
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Isaac Pearson Coleman and James Beakes Coleman were sons of James Coleman and Sarah Beakes Coleman, who were Quakers. Isaac Coleman was born near Trenton, New Jersey, February 2, 1804. He received his early education at the Trenton Academy, studied medicine under Dr. Francis A. Ewing of Trenton, and obtained his medical degree from Yale in 1832. He first practiced medicine in Trenton, and about 1837, settled in Pemberton, New Jersey. In 1843 he married Anne Saltar of Philadelphia. They had three children. Isaac Coleman was a surgeon as well as physician and served as president of the Medical Society of New Jersey. He died November 4, 1869.
James Beakes Coleman was born October 6, 1805 in Trenton, New Jersey where he received his early education. He worked under an apothecary where he obtained a knowledge of practical chemistry. He studied medicine under Dr. Nicholas (de) Belleville of Trenton, and received his M.D. from Yale in 1829. After graduation, he began practicing medicine in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Two years later he relocated to Juliustown in Burlington County, New Jersey. In 1837, he settled in Trenton where he practiced medicine and surgery for the rest of his life. He was a general practitioner, who, like his brother, was known for his surgical skill. He married Henrietta Beasley and had several children including Waldburg Coleman who became a physician. James Coleman was president of the Board of Health in Trenton, a member of the Board of Managers of the New Jersey State Lunatic Asylum, founding member and president of the District Medical Society of Mercer County, New Jersey, and president of the Medical Society of New Jersey in 1855. He was also a talented amateur portrait artist and caricaturist. He died December 19, 1877.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the correspondence between the brothers and Yale-educated physicians Isaac Pearson Coleman and James Beakes Coleman of New Jersey spanning their years at the Medical Institution of Yale College (Yale University School of Medicine) through the beginnings of their respective medical practices in New Jersey; their correspondence with other practitioners and members of their families; extended family correspondence; James Coleman's notes and lectures on phrenology; and a large number of documents including deeds, miscellaneous printed matter, and receipts of Isaac Coleman and his family, the brothers' parents and their ancestors; and 33 photographs of the extended family. (There are no photographs of the Coleman brothers). The letters particularly document Isaac P. Coleman's time at Yale (1829-1832). Notable professional correspondents include preceptors, Dr. Francis A. Ewing of Trenton and Dr. Thomas Story Kirkbride, a Philadelphia psychiatrist who had also studied medicine with Nicholas Belleville in Trenton. Medical topics include medical education, anatomy and dissection, New Jersey licensing law, medical treatments, smallpox and vaccination, and phrenology.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: 1. Correspondence of Isaac and James Coleman. 2. Correspondence of the extended Coleman family. 3. Manuscripts and documents of the Coleman brothers and family. 4. Letters and documents related to the parents and ancestors of the Coleman brothers. 5. Photographs.
Burlington County (N.J.); Dissection; Medical education -- Connecticut -- 19th century; Medical colleges -- Connecticut; Phrenology; Medicine -- Practice; Physicians -- New Jersey; Surgery -- Practice; Correspondence; Deeds; Indentures; Photographs; Physicians -- New Jersey; Surgeons -- New Jersey; Beeks family; Coleman family; Saltar family; Coleman, Isaac Pearson, 1804-1869; Coleman, James Beakes, 1805-1877; Coleman, Margaret Ann Emlen Saltar, 1816-1904; Coleman, Sarah Pearson; Coleman, Elizabeth R.; Ewing, Francis A. (Francis Armstrong), -1857; Hubbard, Thomas, 1776-1838; Ives, Eli, 1779-1861; Kirkbride, Thomas Story, 1809-1883; Knight, J. (Jonathan), 1789-1864; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Tully, William, 1785-1859; Yale College (1718-1887). Medical Institution; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Correspondence of Isaac and James Coleman, 1821-1872; 1.
  - Letters from Isaac P. Coleman to James B. Coleman, 1824-1833 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    21 items. Isaac Coleman was engaged in various businesses in Burlington, New Jersey (1824) and Rochester, New York (ca. 1825-1828), before deciding in 1829 to study medicine at Yale over the University of Pennsylvania (see letter dated September 1829). There are 10 letters from New Haven in which he mentions Jonathan Knight, Eli Ives, Benjamin Silliman, and William Tully. Knight served as a preceptor. Coleman received his M.D. in 1832. In 1833, while living in Trenton, he was attending lectures at the "Lyceum," including those "on the mind" and phrenology.
  - Letters from Isaac P. Coleman to James B. Coleman, undated, bulk 1830-1837 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    23 items. Letters from Isaac Coleman in Trenton to James Coleman in Philadelphia and then in Juliustown, New Jersey. Letters mention Dr. Francis A. Ewing, Dr. Thomas S. Kirkbride, and Dr. Nicholas Belleville, negative views of Jacksonian politics, changes in medical licensing, medical treatments by local physicians, and bleeding versus letting nature taking its course.
  - Letters from James B. Coleman to Isaac P. Coleman, 1824-1868 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    13 items. Three letters are to Isaac in New Haven, two of which discuss smallpox and vaccination. The last four letters are to Isaac in Pemberton.
  - Letters from James B. Coleman to Isaac P. Coleman, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    5 items. Four letters are written from Juliustown before Isaac received his M.D. and the fifth, much later, is addressed to Isaac in Pemberton..
  - Letters to Isaac P. Coleman from his son James P. Coleman and daughter Sarah P. Coleman., ca. 1860-1867 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    7 items: 4 letters from Sarah (Sally) at St. Mary's Hall, 1860 and n.d., and 3 from James, 1867 and n.d.
  - Letters to Isaac P. Coleman from various correspondents, 1825-1872 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    18 items. Includes letters from Anna P. Sherman of New Haven, Francis A. Ewing, his sister Mary Ann, and others.
  - Letters from Isaac P. Coleman to his mother and sisters, to his wife Anne Saltar before and after their marriage, and to others, written from Burlington, Trenton, and Pemberton., ca. 1824-1867 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    14 items. One letter to his family dated 1823 [sic] is from New Haven and mentions professor William Tully.
  - Letters to James B. Coleman, A-C, 1827-1832 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    17 items from T. Abbott, Jr., Philadelphia, A. G. Bristol, New Haven, and cousin "Coke," Philadelphia.
  - Letters to James B. Coleman from his sisters Elizabeth R. and Mary Ann Coleman., 1826-1831 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    9 items.
  - Letters to James B. Coleman, D-H, 1824-1832 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    18 items. Letters from De Retz, Philadelphia, Dr. Francis A. Ewing, Trenton, John M. Fox, Philadelphia, and Alexander Hamilton, New York
  - Letters to James B. Coleman, H-K, 1826-1836 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    15 items. Letters from from Charles Higbee, Trenton, Peter Howell, Trenton, Nathan B. Ives (son of Eli Ives), New Haven (Yale School of Medicine, 1828), Jacob N. Keeler, New Haven (Yale School of Medicimne, 1837), and Dr. Thomas. S. Kirkbride. One letter from Keeler discusses medical education at Yale, including obtaining a body of a "Negro" for dissection, and faculty including the professor of surgery, Thomas Hubbard.
  - Letters to James B. Coleman, M-W, 1821-1834 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    23 items. Letters from "Martinus," Philadelphia, Richard A. Stout, Baltimore, Stephen Y. Watson, Dr. John. G. White, Philadelphia, and Allen Wilson, Trenton. 5 letters from Philadelphia are signed variously as "Martinus Scriblerus," "Martinus," "Cardinal De La Pole," or "De Pole."
  - Letters testifying to the training and character of James B. Coleman, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    These may have been required by Yale.
    - Letter from Dr. Nicholas Belleville testifying that James B. Coleman had studied medicine and surgery for three years under Belleville's supervision, 1830 June 17
    - Letter testifying to James B. Coleman's character by Charles Ewing, Chief Justice of the New Jersey Supreme Court, 1830 June 16
  - Letters to James B. Coleman from miscellaneous others, 1825-1844 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    11 items.
  - Letters from James B. Coleman to sisters Mary Ann Coleman and Elizabeth R. Coleman, 1829-1846 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    4 items,
  - Letters to "Dr. Coleman" (Isaac or James)., 1851-1867 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    7 items. Letters from D. Douglass, Mary H. Bodine, Edward Hallowell, Anne B. Cole, H. Wells, D. I. Parmelee, and John Maclean.
- Correspondence of the extended Coleman family, Series II
  - Letters to Elizabeth R. Coleman, 1847-1883 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    31 items. Elizabeth R. Coleman was the sister of Isaac and James Coleman.
  - Letters to Elizabeth R. Coleman, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    19 items. Several letters are addressed to "Lizzie."
  - Letters from Elizabeth R. Coleman, 1827-1857 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    10 items, 2 undated. Some are addressed to "Dear Sister"
  - Letters to Anne (Saltar) Coleman, 1830-1864 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    29 tems. Margaret Anne Emlem Saltar Coleman, known as Anne or Annie, was the wife of Isaac P. Coleman. Several letters are from Elizabeth R. Coleman, sister of Isaac and James.
  - Letters to/from Anne (Saltar) Coleman, 1841, 1867-1888 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    24 items, 15 undated. One letter from Anne Coleman to her aunt, Frances (Fanny) Saltar, 1841.
  - Letters to Sally Pearson Coleman, 1861-1887 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    29 items. Sally Pearson Coleman was the daughter of Isaac Coleman. See folder 5. Includes two letters describing Civil War duties in the Washington. D.C. area sent by Lewis H. Lightstripe.
  - Letters to Sally Pearson Coleman, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    20 items. Includes an illustrated letter from Frances (Fanny) Saltar with a description of the wedding of Fanny Wharton to Brigadier General Guy V. Henry.
  - Letters from Sally Pearson Coleman, 1859-1867 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    10 items.
  - Miscellaneous Coleman family correspondence, 1849, 1856-1903 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    24 items.
- Manuscripts and documents of the Coleman brothers and family, 1830-1860; Series III
  - Manuscripts by James B. Coleman (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Notes for lecture delivered by Coleman on "The Doctrine of Phrenology.", n.d.
    - A more extensive 41-page manuscript for a two-part lecture on phrenology., n.d.
    - Brief manuscript outlines on the "varieties of men," a racially based typology., n.d.
  - Miscellaneous receipts to Isaac P. Coleman, 1831, 1857-1867 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    80 items. These are mostly handwritten receipts to Isaac Coleman for goods and services. There are many printed receipts for transporting freight from the "Burlington County R.R. & Transportation Co." One note signed by Coleman certified that the death of Mrs. Samuel H.. Jones came "from natural causes alone" (August 6, 1864). The 1831 document is a receipt to [Isaac] Pearson Coleman for $64.00 for claims of both Isaac and James.
  - Larger format receipts to Isaac P.Coleman, 1859-1868 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    54 items. Receipts to Issac P. Coleman similar to folder 26. There are nine tuition bills for the education of James Pearson Coleman under Charles E. Aaron at Mount Holly, New Jersey, 1863-1866, and one bill for tuition at Pemberton Academy, 1867. Also of note are dues receipts from the Burlington County Lyeum of Natural History and a receipt for subscription to the Medical and Surgical Reporter.
  - Tuition bills, grade reports; tax bills; printed documents related to the Civil War, sent to Isaac P. Coleman, 1859-1866 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    18 items, including tuition billls and grades for daughters Sarah (Sally) Pearson Coleman and Anne (Annie) Saltar Coleman at St. Mary's Hall, Burlington; printed booklet: Diocese of New Jersey, St. Mary's Hall, Register (Philadelphia, 1861); tax bills from the Internal Revenue service; printed document from the Star Gazette, Trenton, 1859; large certificate appointing Isaac Coleman and others constituting Council 80, located in Pemberton, of the Union League of America, New Jersey Chapter; and two printed sheets from the Grand National Council Chamber of the Union League regarding the war, 1864; State of New Jersy, Office of the Quartermaster General document requesting volunteer surgical assistance in the war, 1864.
  - Legal documents concerning lands related to Isaac P. Coleman, 1858-1859 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    5 items
  - Miscellaneous manuscript notes and receipts, Isaac Coleman's family, 1859-1865 and n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    13 items. 2 composition books by Sally P. Coleman; stocks of an oil company given to Sally and Annie Coleman, a manuscript Valentine poem.
  - Miscellaneous notes and receipts, 1834-1867 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Manuscript poems, gardening notes, notes on religion, receipts, geological map of "the district between Portage Lake and Montreal River, Lake Superior, Michigan."
  - Miscellaneous legal documents relating to Benjamin F. Boulton, Hannah Lame, James A. Fenwick, Job Gaskill, and Isaac Hilliard, and others, mostly of Burlington County, New Jersey, 1830-1905 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    21 items. Mostly deeds, but also 1905 copies of a 1844 land survey; and a naturalization certificate of Archibald Campbell of Scotland, 1886.
- Letters and documents related to the parents and ancestors of the Coleman brothers, 1743-1910; Series IV
  Edmund Beakes was the great-grandfather of the Coleman brothers. His only child married Job Pearson. Pearson's only child Sarah Beakes Pearson married James Coleman of Maidenhead (later called Lawrence Township) in 1803. James Coleman (died by 1811) and Timothy Coleman of Nottingham, Burlington County, New Jersey, may be the father and uncle of James Coleman of Maidenhead
  - James Coleman and/or Sarah Beakes Coleman: letters and legal documents, 1803-1829 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    9 items. Letters to James Coleman near Trenton or Sarah Beakes Coleman; marriage certificate of James Coleman and Sarah Pearson, 1803; deed to James Coleman of Maidenhead, 1806; Timothy Coleman and Sarah his wife of Amwell, Hunterdon County, deed to James Coleman of Maidenhead to land in Maidenhead, 1805; two conveyances of land by Sarah (Beakes) Coleman, 1829. James and Sarah Beakes Coleman were the parents of the Coleman brothers.
  - Legal documents pertaining to James Coleman and Timothy Coleman, 1775-1811 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    4 items.
    - Indenture to "James Coalman of Nottingham in the County of Burlington and Province of New Jersey", 1775 June 8
    - Indenture to " Timothy Coalman" of Nottingham, 1801 June 13
    - "James Coleman late of the Township of Nottingham" conveyance of land, 1809 August 1
    - James Coleman (son) of Maidenhead, conveyance of land of his late father, James Coleman of Nottingham, 1811 Dercember 26
  - Letter and legal documents pertaining to Edmund Beakes, Job Pearson, and James Coleman, 1723-1801 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Leather bound receipt book used successively by Edmund Beakes, Job Pearson, and James Coleman, 1764-1815
    - Copy of a contract of Edmund Beakes with John Thorne for construction of a house, 1723 August 5
    - Indenture between John Burtham of Rumford County, New Jersey, and Edward Beakes of Trenton conveying property to Beakes, 1753 May 17
    - Will of Edmund Beakes, written 1771
    - Legal document stating money owed by Nicholas Everitt and Ezekial Everitt to Edmund Beakes of Trenton, 1773 March 10
    - Legal bond stating money owed by Isaac Allen and Abraham Hunt to Edmund Beakes of Maidenhead, 1773 May 20
    - Job Pearson, conveyance of property, 1784 February 10
    - Deed to Job Pearson of Maidenhead, 1784 Mrach 1
    - John H. Smith document concerning money owed him by the estate of Edmund Beakes, Job Pearson executor, 1786 April 3
    - Letter of [J.S.?] Pearson to Job Pearson, "near Trenton", 1795 December 15
    - Mary Tindall, widow of Thomas Tindall, late of Maidenhead, release of property to Job Pearson, 1801 May 12
  - Eighteenth-century legal documents possibly related to the Beakes, Pearson, and Coleman families, 1743-1761 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Indenture between Benjamin Flounders to James Wells and others regarding property in England, 1743 December 1
    - Indenture between Benjamin Smith and John Burchem regarding land in Burlington, County, New Jersey, 1751 June 17
    - Indenture between Joshua Knight, Abington Township, Pennsylvania, and Derick Tyson, 1761 May 20
    - Indenture between Thomas Cadwalader of Philadelphia and Thomas Tindall of Maidenhead, New Jersey, 1761 November 23
    - Fragment "Lease Wm Berry to P. Stelle for his mine at Amwel", 1756
- Photographs, Series V
  - Portrait photographs, one 1874, others undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    20 photographs ca. 10 x 6 cm taken by various studios of Margaret Anne Emler Saltar Coleman (wife of Isaac); Annie Saltar Coleman, Sarah Pearson Coleman, and James Pearson Coleman (children of Isaac); John Saltar IV; Susan McLeod; Charles O. Alllibone; Mary Fenwick White; Emily Kinsinger; and Agnes C. Lightstripe. Some photographs are unidentified.
  - Portrait photographs, 1880s and 1890s, some undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    13 photographs by various studios, mostly ca. 17 x 11 cm. Included are Mr. & Mrs. Joseph Saltar, Mary E. Saltar, Howell Bickley, Anita Coleman, Hilda Loveless, Susan McLeod, Elizabeth Coleman White, Mary Fenwick White, Rittmeister Van Roth (Vienna) and fiancee, Robbie Earl, and Queen Victoria with the Princess Beatrice.